本字幕由 ShinY 深影字幕组 原创翻译制作
深影字幕组论坛地址 http://shinybbs.com
翻译： 华青墨 t豆儿 日月
校对： 唱唱反调  后期： 唱唱反调
早上好 哥们儿
Morning, brother.
有什么能帮助您的吗
Can I help you?
你还记得我吗
Do you remember me?
抱歉 我认识你吗
I'm sorry, do I know you?
你认识我吗
Do you know me?
我认识你
I know you.
我认识你 我认识你
know you! I know you!
# 我今早起床 #
I got out of bed today
# 对上帝发誓我看不见我的脸 #
Swear to God I couldn't see my face
# 我今早起床注视着一缕灵魂 #
I got out of bed today staring at a ghost
# 你看到我的灵魂了么 #
Oh have you seen my ghost
# 感觉到它了么 看到它了么 #
Seen my ghost, seen my ghost?
# 你看到我的灵魂了么 它凝视着地面 #
Oh have you seen my ghost staring at the ground?
心灵缉凶 第二季第4集
咱们去吃午餐吧 我请客
Let's go for lunch. On me.
你怎么了
What's with you?
怎么 我不能请队员们吃午餐吗
What I can't buy the team lunch?
不是 只是...
No, it's just...
你在示好 拉倒吧你
you're trying to be nice. Stop it.
不不 别拉倒啊
No, no, don't stop it.
我喜欢友善的艾登 还有免费午餐
I like the nice Aidan. And free lunch?
- 那么我们去哪里呢 - 肯森顿市场
- So, where are we going? - Kensington Market.
- 炸玉米饼吗 - 鸡肉馅饼
- Tacos? - Empanadas.
- 蓄意谋杀 - 是的
- Attempt Murder. - That's right.
今早在肯森顿市场发生一起持刀行凶案件
There was a knife attack in Kensington Market this morning.
受害人被砍了五刀
Victim was slashed 5 times.
缝了一百多针 但没有生命危险
Over 100 stitches, but he'll live.
凭什么分给我们呢 嫌疑人还是受害人
What makes it ours? Suspect, or victim?
对嫌疑人还一无所知 他现在不知所踪
Nothing on the suspect. He's in the wind.
是因为受害人 艾德瑞斯约翰 四十岁
You're on it for the victim - Idaris John, 40.
医疗记录显示他被诊断为患有
Medical records show he's been diagnosed with p...
人 面 失 认...
pro-so-pag-noss...
人面失认症 真的吗
Prosopagnosia. For real?
超罕见的 真有点意思
Huh. It's super rare, really interesting.
对 通俗的说法是" 脸盲 "
Yeah, layman's term is "Face Blindness".
- 比如 - 意思是说 如果你得上了
- As in...? - As in, if you have it,
你就不能辨别任何面部特征
you can't make sense of any facial features.
你分不出谁是谁
You can't tell one person from the other,
除非通过声音
unless you heard their voice
或他们的其他特征来辨认
or recognized some other part of them.
大脑不像本应该的那样
The brain just doesn't process
处理面部特征的视觉信息
the visual information of a face the way it's supposed to.
这通常是神经损伤的征兆
It's often a sign of neurological damage,
例如脑损伤或中风
like a brain injury or a stroke.
好了 你们去市场
OK, you guys get to the Market,
你们俩去医院
you two get down to the hospital,
看能否诱导艾德瑞斯约翰说出些什么
see if you can coax anything out of Idaris John.
我们需要关于攻击者的描述
We need a description of the assailant.
好把他拘捕归案
Let's get this guy off the street.
约翰先生吗
Mr. John?
我认识你吗
Do I know you?
我是马龙医生 替警方工作
I'm Doctor Malone. I work with the police.
这位是韦涅夫斯基警探
This is Detective Wisnefski.
我已经跟一位警官说过了
I already spoke to an officer.
我辩认不出他是谁
I cannot identify this man.
我明白
I understand that.
我看过你的档案摘要
I've read a summary of your file.
你过去四年左右都是这个状态吗
You've had your condition for the last 4 years or so?
我记不清有多久了
I cannot remember how long.
你得去问我的医生
You'll have to ask my doctor.
你能告诉我你望着我的时候看到的是什么吗
Can you tell me what you see when you look at me?
我能看到你完整的面部
You have all the pieces of a face...
鼻子
a nose,
嘴巴
mouth...
以及你的眼睛
and your eyes.
你的眼睛非常特别
You have very unique eyes.
我或许认识你
I might recognize you.
你是怎么处理这些信息的
How do you cope?
我有医生
I have a doctor.
他教我一些技巧 方法
He teaches me tricks, techniques.
辅以声音 首饰
Voices help, jewellery,
纹身
tattoos.
我看你主要是看你的枪
I look at you and mainly I see your gun.
这也是我
It's how I would be
如果再次见到你最有可能认出你的方式
most likely to know you if I see you again.
那个袭击了你的人 你注意到了他的什么
The man who attacked you, what did you notice about him?
他的刀
His knife.
"我认识你" 或者 "你认识我"
"I know you" or "You know me".
这就是目击者们声称他们听到的
That's what the witnesses said that they heard.
有关于疑犯的描述吗
Any description of the suspect?
黑人男子 年龄在十八到四十五之间
Black male. I'm getting ages from 18 to 45,
身高五尺八到六尺二之间
height from 5'8 " to 6'2".
这么说 他们注意到了他是个黑人
So, they noticed he was black.
正如所料 仅此而已
Figures. That's about all.
跑这么老远 砍了艾德瑞斯约翰五刀
You go this far, you slash Idaris John 5 times.
但却不足以杀死他 那么为何住手呢
Not much more to kill him. So, why stop?
刺杀才致命
Stab wounds kill.
他只是砍
He only slashed.
你是什么 嗜血法医吗 你在看鲜血飞溅吗
What are you, Dexter? You're reading blood spatter?
我看医学报告 你医过多少刺伤
I read the medical reports. How many stab wounds have you treated?
如此说来 要么他不知道自己在干啥
So, either he didn't know what he was doing
要么就是不想杀他
or he didn't want to kill him.
或许是想借此传个口信
Maybe he was trying to send a message.
弃妇的汉子 或许艾德瑞斯没出保护费
Jilted husband. Maybe Idaris didn't pay protection.
或许他赌博呢
Maybe he gambles.
也没准艾德瑞斯只是随机被选中的受害人
Or, maybe Idaris was just a random victim.
目击者听到了" 我认识你 "
Witnesses heard "I know you"
和 " 你认识我 "
or "you know me"?
这么说 你觉得是私人恩怨了
So, you think it's personal.
我希望是 可不想是随机挑选的
I hope it's personal. We don't want random.
你们在干什么 艾德瑞斯呢 他没事吧
What are you doing? Where's Idaris? Is he gonna be OK?
没事 我们的人在医院陪着他
OK, our people are with him over at the hospital.
他不会有事的
He's gonna be fine.
你们如何处置他的物品 他什么也没干
What were you doing with his stuff? He didn't do anything.
有人袭击了他 我们只是试图找出原因
Someone attacked him. We're just trying to figure out why.
听着 我们不想给约翰先生制造任何麻烦
Look, we're not trying to cause any trouble for Mr. John.
你在这里工作吗
Do you work here?
对 现在该我值班了
Yeah, my shift was supposed to start now.
- 你叫什么名字 - 茱莉娅
- What's your name? - Julia.
茱莉娅 你知道有谁想伤害你老板吗
Julia, do you know anyone who'd want to hurt your boss?
不知道 人人都爱艾德瑞斯
No. Everybody loves Idaris.
调查警司 我找到些东西
Detective Sergeant? I found something.
- 我觉得是刀头 - 我想我拿到了
- I think the blade's up. - I think I got it.
滚开 会把你们手指打掉的
Get the hell out of here! You'll blow your fingers off!
嘿 艾登 你还好吧
Yo, Aidan. You cool?
没事 伙计
Yeah, man.
只是有点神经质 仅此而已
Just a little jumpy, that's all.
还在做团体倾诉治疗吗
Still doing that group thing?
去得不够
Not enough.
- 你能负责取出来吗 - 可以
- You want to take care of that? - Yeah.
貌似他不止记不住面孔
Seems like it's not just faces he can't remember.
他有短期记忆问题
He has short-term memory problems.
人面失认症可能更大部分是
The prosopagnosia could be part of larger
神经退行性问题
neurodegenerative issues.
打扰一下 我们能帮上忙吗
Excuse me. Can we help you?
我看着像需要帮忙吗
Uh, oh, do I look like I need help?
我们正处于评估的中间环节 如果您能
We're just in the middle of an assessment. If you could
给我们点时间 布鲁克曼医生
just give us a moment, Dr... Bruckmann. Oh,
您专门从事老年病学 对吗
you specialize in geriatrics, right?
对 是的 你们在评估我的患者吗
Yes, I do. You're assessing my patient?
他是一桩犯罪的受害者 我是克拉拉马龙医生
He was a victim in a crime. I'm Dr. Clara Malone.
这位是心理犯案组的韦涅夫斯基警探
This is Detective Wisnefski with Psych Crimes Unit.
那么 您是他的精神科医生对吗
So, you're his psychiatrist?
- 但是他 - 很年轻 对 是的
- But he's... - Young. Yes, he is.
我们来这里是因为脸盲
We're here because of the face blindness.
我们希望他能给出些描述
We'd hoped for some kind of a description out of him.
- 对他而言是不可能的 - 我意识到了
- That's not possible for him. - I realize that,
但是他的记忆有些问题
but he has some memory problems.
脸盲是他初期症状的一种
The prosopagnosia was one of his first symptoms.
接着是记忆丧失 定向障碍
Then memory loss, some disorientation.
- 早发性老年痴呆症吗 - 恐怕是的
- Early-onset Alzheimer's? - I'm afraid so.
- 他怎么会 四十出头吗 - 确实不常见
- He's what, early 40s? - It's not common.
- 但可能致命 - 他患病多久了
- But likely fatal. - How long has he got?
五六年了
Five or six years.
他正进入中期
He's heading into the middle stages.
他的记忆浮现又消失
His memory comes and goes.
这么说 他明天或许会记得更多喽
So, he might remember more tomorrow?
有可能
He might.
但如果你想让他描述的话
But if you're hoping to get a description out of him...
没可能的
that's never gonna happen.
一个符合我们模糊描述的人
A guy matching our vague description, he applied
申请了一份在拐角理发店的清扫工作
for a job sweeping up at a barbershop around the corner.
好啊 我们去找他谈谈
All right, let's go talk to him.
没那么简单 他只留了个电子邮箱
It's not that easy. He only left an email contact.
没有电话号码 没有地址
No phone number, no address.
- 有没有名字呢 - 本
- What about a name? - Ben.
好吧 让波比以理发店老板的身份
All right, I'll have Poppy email him
给他发邮件
as a barbershop owner,
设计一个假面试 引诱他过来
set up a fake interview, lure him in.
等一下 所以你是那么容易就允许撒谎了吗
Wait, so, you're allowed to lie to people that easy?
- 是啊 - 而这不是个圈套吗
- Yeah. - And it's not entrapment?
不 请他来买一斤可卡因才是圈套
No, it's entrapment to invite a guy to buy a key of coke,
但邀请他来工作面试 告诉他他赢了彩票
but invite him to a job interview, tell him he won the lottery,
这都是公平的游戏
that's all fair game.
该死 我该开始好好练练我的说谎技巧了
Damn. I gotta start working on my lying skills.
留给专业人员吧
Leave it to the professionals.
哦 等一下 马上
Oh, hold on, one second.
你承诺过的
You promised.
- 来吧 兄弟 - 好吧
- Come on, man. - All right.
把刀藏起来可不叫做随机犯罪
Hiding the knife doesn't say random.
好吧 这是个理性选择 至少对一个
Well, it's a rational choice. At least, rational for somebody
四处流窜 用刀伤人的人来说是合理的
who goes around attacking people with a knife.
然后就有了那句'我认识你'
Then there's the "I know you".
而艾德瑞斯并不认为这是真的
Which Idaris doesn't think is true.
但是艾德瑞斯是不可信证人
But Idaris is an unreliable witness.
好的 找到与刀上指纹匹配的人了
OK, the prints off the knife got a match.
本杰明奥马里
Benjamin Omari.
一个刚果民主共和国的难民
A refugee from the Democratic Republic of Congo.
他到这六个月了
He's been in the country 6 months.
本 是本
Ben. Ben!
波比 你收到邮件回复了吗
Poppy, did you get a reply to that email?
没有 这孩子还在外面某处 有前科吗
Crickets. The kid's still out there somewhere. Priors?
- 没有 - 那我们怎么得到指纹匹配的
- None. - Then how'd we get a print match?
新的难民法 所有申请人都要取指纹
This new refugee law. Everyone applying for status gets fingerprinted.
而我们可以用那个数据库
And we can access that database?
这是什么 一个极权国家吗
What is this, a police state?
我们匹配上了嫌疑人 我只关心这个
We got a match to our suspect. That's all I care about.
本杰明奥马里有住址吗
Does Benjamin Omari have an address?
所知的最后一处是难民庇护所
Last known was a refugee shelter.
几个月前他被赶了出来 此后就没人见过他
He got kicked out a couple months ago. No one's seen him since.
他是被资助的
He was sponsored coming over;
是一个叫国际司法监控的人权组织
human rights organization called Justice Monitor International.
一个叫索兰格奥乌苏的人帮他签发的
A Solange Owusu signed off on him.
你知道这儿有什么人和他在一块吗
Do you know if there's anyone else here with him?
- 朋友 家人 - 我去拿他的档案
- Friends, family? - I'll get his file.
没人
No one.
他独自一人在这
He's alone here.
能让我看下这个吗
Can I just see that?
哦 上帝 这看起来好像他
Oh, my god. It looks just like him.
是的 那是本 十二岁时
Yes, that's Ben, age 12.
不 不是本 那是谁
No, not Ben. Who's that?
穆萨布图罗
Musa Buturo.
刚果的通缉犯
Wanted for crimes in the Congo.
他被称作梅鲁戈 巫师
He went by the name Melugo. The Wizard.
他是本的指挥官之一 怎么了
He's one of Ben's commanders. Why?
他看起来就像本袭击的那个人
He looks just like the man Ben attacked.
这是艾德瑞斯约翰
That's Idaris John.
你对刚果民主共和国的战役
What do you know about the war in The Democratic
知道些什么
Republic of Congo?
是自二战后伤亡最多的斗争
Most casualties in a conflict since World War II,
而且看不见尽头
and no end in sight.
这人扮演什么角色
What was this man's role?
梅鲁戈是一个反叛民兵的指挥官
Melugo was a commander in the rebel militia
他们杀了几百 更可能是几千人
that has killed hundreds, more likely thousands.
他已经躲藏了好多年了
He's been in hiding for years.
这是唯一已知的他的视频
This is the only known video of him.
这被称为非洲的内战
This has been called Africa's civil war.
数以百万人死去
Millions are dead.
你自己为了你的人民的自由而流血
You yourself have shed blood for the freedom of your people.
你说这是上帝的旨意
You've said it was God's will.
我只说过让我的人民自由是上帝的旨意
I've only said it is God's will for my people to be free.
让他所有的孩子自由正是他的旨意
It is His will for all His children to be free.
你说到孩子们的自由
You talk of freedom for children,
而你却仍在绑架 灌输
and yet you abducted and indoctrinated
数百孩子为你而战 难道不是吗
hundreds of children to fight for your cause. Is that not true?
我没绑架任何人 强迫任何人
I abduct no one. Force no one.
你在这看到孩子
You see children here
是因为我给他们提供了一个安全的处所
because I give them a safe place.
是什么告诉你
What does it tell you
他们寻求武装保护了
that they ask for arms to protect themselves?
在这我们每天都要为生活而战
We fight for our lives here every day.
那你呢
What about you?
你为什么而战
What do you fight for?
你说他在这吗 本袭击的人就是他
And you say he's here? This is the man Ben attacked?
他们非常的相像
The resemblance is very strong.
但是我在现场看过艾德瑞斯的个人档案
But I saw Idaris' personal documents at the scene.
一切看起来都是合法的
Everything looked legit.
这些人不但是盗贼还是杀手
These men are thieves as well as killers.
用他们偷走的东西 他们能买一个新的身份
With what they steal, they can buy a new identity.
所以 梅鲁戈是本的指挥官 然后
So, Melugo was Ben's commander, and then
他彻底改变自己成为艾德瑞斯约翰
he reinvented himself as Idaris John.
这给了我们袭击的动机
Gives us a motive for the attack.
也带来了另一个问题
And it brings up another question:
谁才是这真正的受害者
who's the real victim here?
看起来确实像是同一个人
Well it sure looks like the same guy.
所以 我们对艾德瑞斯约翰了解些什么
So, what do we know about Idaris John?
他在这四年了 水果超市开了三年
He's been here 4 years, he's had the fruit market for 3.
没有犯罪记录 没有移民局标记
There's no record, no flags from Immigration.
这家伙为自己制造了一个可靠的新身份
This guy's created a solid new identity for himself.
好吧 如果是假的 就不可靠
Well, if it's false, it's not solid.
他从哪儿弄来的钱开水果超市呢
Where'd he get the money for the fruit market?
他通过一家信用合作社理财
He runs his finances through a local credit union...
一家分公司 很低调
one branch, low profile.
看起来他把钱藏在海外了
Looks like he's got money stashed offshore,
- 但我看不到细节 - 第一个问题是
- but I can't get the details. - First question is:
我们怎么确认艾德瑞斯约翰就是梅鲁戈
How do we confirm that Idaris John is Melugo?
我们有视频
We have the video.
是 但里面没说他的名字 而且也没有
Yeah, but he's not mentioned by name, and it's no proof
他被指控所犯罪行的证据 所以我恐怕
of the crimes he's accused of committing, so we're not
我们无法从里面得到真凭实据
going to get much hard evidence from there, I'm afraid.
那我们得找到本奥马里 他能确认
Then we need to find Ben Omari. He can confirm that
艾德瑞斯是他的前指挥官并使这个视频合法化
Idaris is his former commander and legitimize this video.
所以 唯一能让这视频与艾德瑞斯联系上的
So, the only guy who can pin this on Idaris
就是那个袭击了他被通缉的人
is the one wanted for attacking him.
你有他的消息吗
Have you heard from him?
还没回复面试 我一点儿也不惊讶
Still no reply to the job interview. I'm not surprised.
- 我可以试试告诉他被聘用了 - 好吧
- I could try telling him he's hired? - All right,
那么等确认了艾德瑞斯的身份 然后呢
so when we do ID Idaris, then what?
我们能把他驱逐出境吗
Can we deport him?
如果我们能证明他是战犯
If we can prove he's a war criminal
而且他没有接受处决
and he's not facing execution for his crimes.
没有那么快 由鉴于他的精神状况
Not so fast. With his mental condition,
他可以以就医为由反对驱逐出境
he can fight deportation on medical grounds.
- 你开玩笑呢吧 - 这是法律
- You gotta be kidding me. - It's the law.
这多方便啊
How convenient is that?
如果他是装的呢
What if he's faking?
艾德瑞斯在他到这后不久
Idaris started seeing Dr. Bruckmann
就开始在布鲁克曼医生看病 那就是四年来
not long after he arrived. That's 4 years
愚弄一个在该领域相当著名的专家 不太可能
of fooling a fairly well-known expert in the field. Not likely.
好吧 可这些都是不可能的啊 我们的受害者
OK, but none of this is likely. Our victim is
是一个战犯 而攻击者是他的前童子军
a war criminal, our assailant is his former child soldier.
正如索兰格所说 这家伙是个老练的骗子
And like Solange said, this guy's a practiced liar.
好吧 如果他是装的 我们就得证明
OK, if he's faking, then we've got to prove it.
我可以评估他
I can assess him.
艾德瑞斯
Idaris.
我认识你吗
Do I know you?
不认识吗
Don't you?
马龙医生
Dr. Malone.
你的眼睛 我告诉过你的
Your eyes. I told you.
我为什么在这
Why am I here?
我能给你看几幅图吗
Can I show you some pictures?
你认识这些人吗
Do you recognize anyone here?
我认识其中的哪一个吗
Do I know one of them?
我相信你全认识
I believe you know all of them.
我不认识
I do not know.
你认得出他吗
Do you recognize this one?
他怎么了
How about him?
- 是袭击我的那个人吗 - 不 这是你
- Is that the man who attacked me? - No. This one is you.
好的 不再有人脸了
OK, no more faces.
- 谢谢 结束了吗 - 还没有
- Thank you. Are we done? - Not quite.
我想让你画个钟给我
I'd like you to draw a clock for me.
画个简单的就行
Just a simple one.
没我的医生说的那么糟 对吗
Not so bad as my doctor says, am I?
你做得很好
You're doing fine.
那么 我刚刚看到什么了
So, what did I just see?
他的症状就是教科书上的
His symptoms are textbook.
- 每个细节都很符合 - 这正常吗
- Every detail was exactly right. - Is that normal?
人脑唯一不变的特质
Well, the only thing consistent with the human brain
就是其不一致性 所以不 不正常
is its inconsistency, so no, it's not.
- 所以他在说谎 - 不是我能证明的
- So, he's lying. - Not so I can prove it.
检查结果与他之前的诊断一致
The test confirmed his diagnosis.
别管检查 你的直觉是什么
Screw the test. What's your gut tell you?
直觉不准确
It doesn't work that way.
克拉拉 我是说你望着这个人时看到了什么
Clara, I mean, you look at this guy, what do you see?
- 他到底病了没有 - 我不知道 艾登
- Is he sick, or not? - I don't know, Aidan.
我好像是在透过面具看人
It's like I'm looking at a mask.
那我们怎么把面具拿掉
So, how do we take it off?
我跟律师聊过了
I spoke with Legal.
克拉拉是对的
Clara is right.
我们不能单单依据一个诊断就把人驱逐出境
We can't deport someone with his diagnosis.
那我们就要将他就地送审
Then we need to put him on trial right here.
这个人是战犯啊 戴安娜
This guy's a war criminal, Dianne.
战争法到目前为止只定罪过一次
The War Crimes Act has resulted in one conviction ever,
那次还有多个目击证人指证
and that was a case with multiple witnesses.
由于艾德瑞斯有神经障碍
With Idaris' neurological disorder,
他可能从未上庭受审过
he may never even see the inside of a courtroom.
或者这次就逃不过了
Or maybe he will.
你还记得我说过艾德瑞斯的症状很典型吗
You remember I said Idaris' symptoms were textbook?
- 记得 - 这里一个病人的描述
- Yeah. - A patient in here describes
与艾德瑞斯的病情描述完全一致
her condition with the exact same words Idaris used with me.
你是说他可能从书上读来的症状
So, you're saying he read the book?
有这个可能
Maybe, yes.
他给我画了这个 你们看
He drew this for me. Look.
别告诉我这是巧合
OK, don't try and tell me that's a coincidence.
连细节都一样 不太可能是巧合
To this level of detail? Can't be.
也就是说他在装
So, he's faking.
这可行么 装了四年
Is that plausible? Four years?
这个人知道他在做什么
Look, this guy knows what he's done. He knew
他知道有一天可能会被抓到
the odds were he'd be found out someday,
所以他提前编好了说辞
so he set himself up in advance.
他生病了 不能被遣送
He's a sick man, can't be deported,
甚至都不能受审
maybe not even fit to stand trial here.
那个多年逍遥法外的暴徒
Who was that mobster that walked around for years
穿着浴袍自言自语的
in his bathrobe talking to himself,
还是组织首领的那个人是谁来着
running his organization the whole time?
文尼希甘特 他的伎俩就成功了
Vinny Gigante, and it worked.
即使艾德瑞斯想这样 那没人帮忙他也做不到
Even if he wanted to, Idaris couldn't do this without help.
- 你在说什么 - 这本书的作者之一
- What are you saying? - One of the contributors
是他的医生的保罗布鲁克曼
to the book is his doctor, Paul Bruckmann.
你认为他受布鲁克曼指使
You think Bruckmann coached him?
我觉得有必要一问
I think we have to ask.
达拉奇斯夫人 我们下周见
So, we'll see you next week, Mrs. Dalakis.
好的 再见
OK, bye-bye.
你好 马龙医生你好 这位是...
Oh, hello, Dr. Malone. And...?
布莱克警官
Detective Black.
- 能聊聊吗 - 嗯 下一个病人来之前
- Can we have a word? - Well, I've got
- 我有十分钟间歇 - 太好了
- 10 minutes between patients. - Perfect.
哇 看
Oh, wow, look at those.
太棒了 是老年精神病学联盟奖么
Amazing. Is that an AGPA?
2009年 是的
Two thousand and nine, yes.
老年精神病学联盟奖 真了不起
Affiliation of Geriatric Psychiatry Award. Very big deal.
非常厉害
Impressive.
是这样的 我们跟艾德瑞斯沟通很难
So, we're having a hard time getting through to Idaris,
我在想
and I'm wondering if,
除去老年痴呆症造成的记忆丧失之外
in addition to memory lapses associated with Alzheimer's,
可能还存在一些文化差异的问题
there may be some transcultural issues.
你知道他在非洲的生活么
Do you know anything about his life in Africa?
有什么事情可能会影响他对这次袭击的反应么
Anything that might be affecting the way he's processing the attack?
我知道他来自于一个动荡的地方
I know he comes from an unstable area,
他以难民的身份逃到这里
that he fled under refugee status.
我只能推测他有很坎坷的经历
I'd assumed his story was not a pleasant one.
也就是说治疗期间
But you didn't specifically deal with
你没有具体问到他的过去了
any of that during the course of treatment?
我主要关注他的精神损伤
My focus has been on his mental deterioration...
他的应对机制 以及他的人脸识别障碍
coping mechanisms for it, and his prosopagnosia.
实际的治疗策略 当然
Practical therapeutic strategies, sure.
但是说实在的 他从没提过他的过去
But really, his past never came up?
没有具体说过
Not specifically, no.
也就是说你并不知道艾德瑞斯约翰是
So you're not aware that Idaris John is
被通缉的战犯咯
a wanted war criminal?
什么
What?
你就没想过
Has it occurred to you
艾德瑞斯可能只是想逃过惩罚
that Idaris could be malingering to escape prosecution?
我怎么会想到呢
How could that occur to me?
太荒谬了
That's ridiculous.
艾德瑞斯给我画了这幅画
Idaris did this drawing for me.
你出版的一本书里
You published a very similar image
有一副相似的画 还有印象吧
in one of your books, didn't you?
其实 应该不只是相似吧
Fact is, it's more than similar, isn't it?
我们知道他在装病
We know he's faking,
布鲁克曼医生 你为何不告诉我们真相
Dr. Bruckmann, so why don't you just tell us the truth?
- 你在暗示我说谎吗 - 我什么也没暗示
- You're insinuating that I'm not? - I'm not insinuating anything.
我在指控你串谋和妨碍司法公正
I'm accusing you of collusion and obstruction of justice.
不 你在口出狂言
No, you're spouting conspiracy fantasies.
- 艾德瑞斯约翰... - 是一个病人
- Idaris John... - Is a very sick man.
我不打算继续这段谈话了
And I'm not going to continue this conversation.
我觉得你们两个更需要接受治疗
If you ask me, it's the two of you who need some help.
谢谢
Thank you.
他在说谎
He's lying.
一定是的 他很害怕 而且不只怕我们
Definitely. And he's scared too, and not just of us.
他辅导艾德瑞斯约翰四年了
Four years he's been coaching Idaris John.
究竟什么使他这样放弃了医德良心
What do you got to pay a doctor to betray his oath like that?
问得好
Good question.
我们肯定要去查查他的财政情况 怎么了
We'll definitely check his finances. What's up?
你们还在布鲁克曼的办公室么
You still at Bruckmann's office?
正要离开 怎么了
We're just leaving now. Why?
我有理发店本的消息了
I got a response from Ben on the barbershop job.
两分钟前他在一个市场的网吧里面发了邮件
Email was sent 2 minutes ago from a web café in the market,
就在你们附近 我把地址发过来
right near you. I'll text you the address.
本 把管子放下
Ben, put the pipe down.
听我说
Listen to me.
我知道你为什么那样做 我知道梅鲁戈
I know why you did what you did. I know about Melugo.
我需要你跟我走一趟
I need you to come with me.
我想听听你有什么想说的
I want to listen to what you have to say.
不
No.
别再犯错了
Look, don't make another bad choice.
艾登 他是个当兵的
Aidan, he's a soldier,
用命令和恐吓胜过说服
wired for commands, intimidation over reason.
好 明白了
All right, I got this.
本 放下管子
Ben, I need you to put that pipe down.
不 不 你退后
No. No, you stay back!
放下
Put it down.
退后 我杀过人
Stay back! I've killed men before!
伙计 听我说 放下管子
Listen to me, man, put that pipe down!
放下 本
Put it down, Ben.
放下管子
Put the pipe down.
本奥马里 你被捕了
Ben Omari, you're under arrest.
本 你麻烦大了
Ben, you're - you''re facing some pretty serious charges.
- 你差点杀了人 - 不 我给他留了活口
- You nearly killed a man. - No, I let him live.
你万幸他还活着
And you're lucky he did.
发生了什么
What happened?
你没胆了么
Did you lose your nerve?
不是 他更应该受折磨
Never. He should suffer.
他应当活在恐惧中
He should live in fear.
你确定不要那个三明治吗
You sure you don't want that sandwich?
你要不吃我可吃了
'Cause, I mean, I'll eat it if you don't.
跟我谈谈他吧 他的名字叫梅鲁戈
Tell me about him. His name is Melugo,
对吧
is that right?
本 我知道你过得很艰难
Ben, I know you've had a rough life.
我没办法想象你经历了什么
I can't even begin to imagine what you've been through,
这些经历如何影响了...
and how it's affected...
每个人都想让我谈以前的生活
Look, everyone wants me to talk about my life from before.
我受够了 都过去了
I am done with that.
就这样
That is all.
你说都过去了 但是你用刀
You say you're done with it, but you just attacked a man
- 捅伤了一个人 - 不关你的事
- with a knife. - It's not your concern.
我能理解淡忘一些事很难
I know it's not easy to walk away from things.
我能理解那种被不断纠缠折磨的感觉
I know what it's like to be haunted.
你为什么不杀他
Why didn't you kill him?
我本来是要杀的
I was going to!
他让我困惑了
He made me confused.
他怎么让你困惑的
How did he do that?
他不记得我了
He didn't remember me.
他不记得你 但是...
He didn't remember you, and... and he should have
他应该记得 对吧
remembered you, is that right?
我过去一直听他指挥
All of those things that I did were his orders.
本 如果你再看到他...
Ben, if you saw him again...
你还能指认他是你的司令官么
would you swear that he was your commander?
你可以签个文书么
Would you sign a paper?
可以
Yes.
我愿意
I would.
没有不敬之意 但是我不懂有什么意义
With respect, I do not see the point.
你知道我没有办法辨别他
You know I cannot identify him.
也许你可以辨别他的声音
Maybe you'll recognize his voice.
他的衣服 或者仪态
An article of clothing. Maybe a mannerism.
我明白了
I see.
我尽力
I will try.
那是他么
Was that him?
是他
Yes.
- 你看见了吗? - 我看见了 他退缩了
- Did you see that? - I saw it. He flinched.
太好了 我们趁热打铁
All right. Let's turn up the heat.
开始吧
Go ahead.
我认识你 我认识你
I know you. I know you.
你听过他的声音吗
Do you recognize his voice?
我可能之前听过这个声音 也可能没有
It might be the voice I heard, it might not.
这一切来得太突然了
It all happened so quickly.
来 我们坐下
OK, let's sit down.
还有别的事情吗 警部
Is there anything else, Inspector?
还有一件事
There is one thing. You say
你说你不认识他 但是这个年轻人却认识你
you can't identify him, but this young man says he can identify you.
- 是吗 - 是
- Oh? - Mm-hmm.
他说你是个战争罪犯
He claims you're a war criminal
并且你在他十二岁时绑架了他
and that you abducted him when he was 12 years old.
他知道你的名字 是什么来着
He says he knew you by the name of... what was it?
梅鲁戈
Melugo.
真让人不安 太惨了
So disturbed, so sad.
我真替这个男孩感到遗憾
I truly feel sorry for this boy.
他袭击了你 你还真是宽宏大量
That's generous, considering he attacked you.
我也当过童子军 你知道吗?
I was a child soldier also. Did you know that?
我们不知道
No, we didn't.
我被征兵
I was recruited.
我打过仗
I fought.
我迷失过方向
I lost my way.
但是我被释放了
But I was freed.
但你又来到这里
But you made it here.
你现在安全了
You're safe.
好像你已经把过去都忘记了
Seems like you've wiped the slate clean,
你开始了全新的生活
like you've made a whole new life.
这么说可能没用 但就我而言
It might not make a difference, but for my part,
我一点都不想指控那个男孩
I do not wish to press any charges against that boy.
我现在能回家了吗
May I go home now?
他什么反应
So, how'd he react?
艾德瑞斯无法掩饰他撒谎时的兴奋
Idaris can't hide the pleasure he takes in lying.
他毫无意识的笑了
He smiles without knowing it.
我们叫做"骗子的快乐"
We call it "Duper's Delight."
但我们对此无计可施
Well, we can't do anything with that.
没错 但是在电梯边我们都看到了 他认识本
No. But we both saw it at the elevator. He knew Ben.
我们发现他有一段时间表现的措手不及
We caught him off guard for a minute,
然后在观察室里 他又恢复了冷静
and then in the observation room he was back in control.
那我们要离他远点
OK, so we gotta take it away from him. Rattling his cage
然后直戳他的弱点 直到他露出马脚
until he cracks and drops his charade.
艾登 他很会装
He's good, Aidan.
我知道这该是我的活儿 但我不知如何解决
I know this is my problem, but I don't know how to solve it.
我会一直监视他 他是人
I'm gonna put a fulltime tail on him. He's human,
他一定会露出尾巴的
he'll screw up eventually.
我们到时候只要在场就行
We just need to be there.
我们可能应经被自己束缚
We may have already tipped our hand.
如果我们步步紧逼 他可能会以新的身份逃走
We go further, he could be on a plane with a new identity.
不 他跑了 我们也会找到他
No. He runs, we'll be on him.
少吃点糖 它会要了你的命
Go easy on that sugar. It's gonna kill you.
快点 我们找个座位坐下
All right, let's take a seat.
你好 艾登 好久不见
Hey, Aidan. It's been a while.
- 是啊 - 又公务缠身了吗
- Yeah, yeah. - Working too much again?
有一点 但是 你知道的
Little bit. But, you know,
我既然来了就要做最大的努力
I'm here now, trying to make the most of it.
当然
Yeah, sure, of course.
各位
OK, everybody,
我想我们要开始了
I guess we'll get started.
大家已经认识彼此了吧
I think everybody knows each other.
艾登
Aidan,
看样子你有话要说
you look like you might want to say something.
是的
Uh, yeah, no, I do.
大家知道 我已经来这里...
Well, you know, I've been coming here for a...
有一段时间了
for a while now, and, uh...
嗨 你好
Hi there.
有事吗
Everything cool?
有人告诉我这个地方比较适合我
I met a guy that said this would be a good place for me.
当然 快进来
Yeah, sure. Of course. Come on in.
快进来 坐下
Come on in, take a seat.
欢迎
Welcome.
艾登刚刚有话要说
Uh, Aidan was just gonna say something.
是的 没关系
Yeah. Uh, you know, it's OK.
我可以以后说
I can wait. Um...
老兄 不如你先来吧
Why don't you go, man?
告诉我们...发生了什么
Tell us what's... what's going on.
他是不是认出我们了
Did he just make us?
- 我没看出来 - 很难说
- I didn't see anything. - Hard to tell.
就像有关这个人的所有事情一样
Like everything else with this guy.
昨晚怎么样 发生什么事了吗
How was last night? You had a thing?
没有 一切还算顺利
Yeah, no, it was... it was good.
你呢 你好像整晚没睡
How about you? You look like you've been up all night.
我上网阅读了
I went online and read every paper
关于保罗布鲁克曼博士的所有论文
I could find by Dr. Paul Bruckmann.
然后呢
And?
时间过得真慢
The clock thing was lazy.
就像用别的病人的一系列症状
So was coaching Idaris
来辅导艾德瑞斯
in another patient's exact set of symptoms.
他很败坏 但是不够彻底
He's corrupt, but he's not thorough.
我们若能在艾德瑞斯身上找到布鲁克曼的文件
If we can get access to Bruckmann's files on Idaris,
我发誓我可以打败他
I swear I can break him.
有没有人跟你说过 你已经成为一名好警察了
Anyone ever tell you you would've made a good cop?
现在有了
Not until now.
波比 出什么事了
What's up, Poppy?
你想利用布鲁克曼博士
You wanted leverage on Dr. Bruckmann.
我想我们成功了
I think we got it.
他每月都会从一个海外账户转账回来
Monthly transfers to him from an offshore account.
我猜每次转账时艾德瑞斯都在这里
Let me guess, going back as long as Idaris has been here.
- 是的 - 我们已经发现艾德瑞斯
- Yep. - OK, so, we've got Idaris
付钱让医生帮他隐藏病情了
paying the doctor to help him fake his condition.
查明这能否足够拘捕他
Find out if that's enough for a warrant.
克莉格拉正在调查此事
Caligra's looking into it.
证据转移的许可证很难搞到手
Admissible proof of the transfers is tricky.
好吧 让里奥赶快过来
All right, get Leo and get down here.
你们继续监视艾德瑞斯 干的好
You guys stay with Idaris. Good work.
那我们现在要做什么 等着吗
So, what do we do now? Wait?
不 我们现在出击
No way. We hit him now.
告诉他授权这就批下来了 让他好好想想后果
Tell him the warrant's coming and let him think through the consequences.
- 让我进去打主场 - 没问题
- Let me take the lead in there. - You got it.
布鲁克曼博士
Dr. Bruckmann?
哦 天啊
Oh, my god.
如果艾德瑞斯发现我们在监视他
If Idaris figured out that we were on to him,
布鲁克曼是唯一能揭示他谎言的人
Bruckmann was the only one who could testify that he was faking.
所以艾德瑞斯除掉了这个软肋
So Idaris cuts the weak link.
现在布鲁克曼死了
But now that Bruckmann's gone,
或许我们可以排除他的假诊断
I mean, maybe we can get rid of his phony diagnosis.
从布鲁克曼被杀的样子来看
I mean, the way Bruckmann was killed, right
就在他的桌子后面 他一定跟杀手很熟
at his desk,from behind. he had to be comfortable with the killer.
应该是他认识的人 像一个朋友 或者...
It's like it was somebody he knew, like a friend, or...
一个病人
Like a patient.
弟兄们
Hey, guys.
你们看看这个
You gotta see this. Julia Grieveson,
茱莉娅格瑞维森是艾德瑞斯的员工
the girl who works for Idaris.
在她父母车祸去世后
She started seeing Bruckmann
她开始来布鲁克曼这里(做心理辅导)
after her parents died -car crash.
现在她和祖母住在一起
Now she lives with her grandmother.
这就是线索
That's the connection.
艾德瑞斯之前在寻找一个容易说服的年轻助手
Idaris was on the hunt for an impressionable young helper.
布鲁克曼给他和一个刚成孤儿的孩子牵线搭桥
And Bruckmann set him up with a brand-new orphan.
他仍然利用儿童来为他效命
He's still using children to fight his battles.
她才十六岁 你真觉得是杀了这个男人
She's 16. You really think she killed a man?
本在比她更小的时候就参加战争了
Ben was fighting a war when he was younger than that.
你做得很好 没有在布鲁克曼博士的办公室里
You did a good job in not leaving any fingerprints
留下指纹
in Dr. Bruckmann's office.
茱莉娅 你很聪明
You're smart, Julia.
但是你知道你每天会掉多少头发吗?
But did you know that you can lose a hundred hairs in a day?
我们在犯罪现场的血泊里发现了一根头发
And that we found a hair in the blood at the crime scene?
我们会证明那是你的头发
And I think we're gonna find out that that hair belongs to you.
但我不明白的是
But what I don't understand
你已经有一年没见到布鲁克曼博士了
is that you haven't been to see Dr. Bruckmann in a year.
为什么要回来
So, why go back now?
是受人指使的吗
Did someone tell you to?
头发的事她信了吗
Did she fall for the hair thing?
- 她什么也没说 - 她在保护他
- But she's not talking. - She's protecting him.
他也再为她做同样的事 对吗
Oh, 'cause he'd do the same thing for her, right?
所以我们要让她相信
That's what we need to convince her...
她对艾德瑞斯来说并不特别 他只是再利用她
that she's not special to Idaris, that he's using her.
- 那我们要怎么做 - 本怎么样
- So, how do we do that? - What about Ben?
像艾德瑞斯这样的人
A guy like Idaris,
这么多年来让孩子们为他效命
been bringing kids
也许用的都是相同的方法
under his power for years, probably uses the same methods.
本知道是什么伎俩
And Ben knows what they are.
波比 把他提审出来
Poppy, go pull him out of holding.
跟我说说梅鲁戈
Tell me about Melugo,
那个自称是艾德瑞斯约翰的男人
the man who calls himself Idaris John.
你第一次见到他是什么时候
When was the first time you saw him?
我十二岁的时候
When I was 12.
梅鲁戈率领了一队民兵进了我们村
Melugo led a militia into my village.
他们杀了所有成年人
They shot all the adults.
其中有些杀手甚至比我还小
Some of them shooting were even younger than I was.
你的父母呢
Your parents?
我目睹了他们被杀
I saw them killed.
我没哭
I didn't cry,
他们把我带去营地时也没哭
not even when they took me to their camp.
在那发生了什么事
What happened there?
他们给我们东西喝 给烟抽
They gave us things to drink and to smoke...
直到我忘了我在哪里
until I forgot about where I was,
忘了我是谁
or who I was.
他们跟我说我是个战士
They told me I was a warrior,
告诉我说我不需要家人 他们就是我的家人
that I didn't need family, that they were my family.
我们跟你祖母谈过了 茱莉娅
You know, we've been talking to your grandmother, Julia, and, um...
她可没说什么好话
she didn't have a lot of nice things to say.
她说你从开始为艾德瑞斯工作就变了
She said you changed when you started working for Idaris.
你跟她断绝来往 是真的吗
You closed off from her. Is that true?
她若这么说 那一定就是了
If she says so, it must be.
艾德瑞斯有没有跟你说你不再需要她了
Did Idaris tell you that you didn't need her anymore?
他才是你唯一需要的家人
That he was the only family that you needed?
反正她从未想要过我
She never wanted me anyway.
她还告诉我们说你吸毒了
She also told us that you got into drugs.
她拿到了一份检测报告
She got one of those tests,
就是你送去化验的 并被发现有冰毒
where you send it to the lab, and they found methamphetamine,
大麻和可卡因
marijuana, cocaine.
是艾德瑞斯给你的吗
Did Idaris get those for you?
你根本不明白
You don't understand.
第一次
The first time,
梅鲁戈让我和另外一个男孩在一个房间
Melugo put me into a room with another boy.
那个男孩曾试图逃跑
A boy who had tried to escape him.
梅鲁戈 也就是 艾德瑞斯
Melugo - Idaris...
他给了我一把弯刀
he gave me a machete.
然后他带着汽油出去了
He went outside with gasoline.
他说我有五分钟的时间提着那个男孩的脚出来
He said I had 5 minutes to come out with the boy's feet,
不然就把我们都烧死
or he would burn us both.
如你所见 医生 我没被烧死
As you can see, Doctor, I have no burns.
他有没有告诉你他为何这样做
Did he tell you why he did that?
他说如果我杀生够多
He told me if I killed enough times...
我就该学会不哭
that I would learn not to cry,
从我杀死的人身上汲取力量
that I would take the strength of those who I had killed.
我们还在你的花园棚里发现了些东西
We also found some things in your garden shed.
你知道我说的是什么吗
Do you know what I'm talking about?
动物的骨骼
Animal skeletons.
老鼠 松鼠
Rats, squirrels...
还有猫
a cat.
看样子它们都是被杀死的
They all looked like they had been killed.
我不知道你在说什么
I don't know what you're talking about.
是艾德瑞斯让你这么做的吗
Did Idaris tell you to do that?
你杀得够多 就学会不再哭泣
That if you did it enough times, you'd learn not to cry?
是他告诉你要从那些动物身上汲取力量吗
Did he tell you that you'd take on the strength of those animals?
因为那是个谎言 茱莉娅 我觉得你是知道的
Because that's a lie, Julia, and I think you know it.
他在别的地方跟其他孩子也说这个谎
And that's a lie that he's told other kids in other places.
我知道他跟你说你是特别的
And I know that he told you that you are special,
但你确实是特别的 茱莉娅
and you are special, Julia,
不过不是对他而言
but not to him.
我每天跟罪犯打交道
I deal with people who commit crimes every day.
有一些
Some...
是好人做了坏事
are good people who have done bad things,
而另外一些
but others...
多数精神病学家不相信善恶
Most psychiatrists don't believe in good and evil.
但是我信
But I do.
并且据我所知
And the one thing I have learned
善恶之间并无高墙
is there is no great wall between them.
如果你能跨步出线
If you can step over the line...
那么也能退后
You can step back.
我知道你是个好人
I know you're a good person.
我也知道如果不是为了艾德瑞斯
And I know you wouldn't have done these things
你也不会做这些事情
if it wasn't for Idaris,
但是我要听你说出来
But I need to hear it from you.
他跟我说这是保护他
He told me that it was the only way
免受敌人迫害的唯一方式
to protect him from his enemies.
他告诉我必须杀死布鲁克曼医生
He told me I had to kill Dr. Bruckmann.
监视汇报说艾德瑞斯出门了
Surveillance said Idaris just left his house,
去了茱莉娅家 跟祖母谈了一下
went to Julia's, spoke to the grandmother,
现在他向西奔着邓达斯去了
now he's headed west on Dundas.
他要逃跑 或许会去机场方向
He's gonna make a run for it. Probably headed to the airport.
我打赌 是信用社 他要跑路 一定需要钱
My bet, the credit union. If he's gonna rabbit, he'll need money.
我们去那儿
Let's get there.
- 进展如何 - 他要出来了
- How we doing? - He's coming out now.
现在你认识我了吗
You recognize me now?
艾登 艾登 抓住他了
Aidan! Aidan, I got him!
抓住他了
I got him.
# 你咆哮发出的回音 #
The echo to your yell
# 你潜水产生的涟漪 #
The ripple to your dive
# 你摇摆下的涌流 #
The currents under your wave
你是茱莉娅吗
You're Julia?
对
Yes.
你吓坏了
You're frightened.
谢谢
Thank you.
如果你愿意 我可以去探望你
And I could come to visit you, if you like.
好 我很愿意
Yeah, I would.
来吧 茱莉娅
Come on, Julia.
该走了
It's time to go.
# 我能感觉到你 #
I could feel you
# 包围着我 #
All around me
要把她怎么着
What will happen to her?
她还未成年
Well, she's a minor,
而且会考虑艾德瑞斯的影响因素
and Idaris' influence will be taken into account,
所以她仍有机会享受美好人生
so she's still got a chance at a good life.
你也一样 本
So do you, Ben.
所以我才逃跑 所以我才来这里
That is why I escaped, why I came here.
我已经没机会了
I haven't had the chance yet.
本 我们已经跟检察官谈过了
Ben, we've been talking to the prosecutors.
他们会重新定罪
They're going to reconsider the charges.
可是与此同时
But in the meantime,
你必须得去做些心理辅导
you're going to have to get some counselling.
多倾诉
More talk.
倾诉不是软弱 本 躲藏才是
Talking is not a weakness, Ben; hiding is.
我安排人来做你的倾诉对象
I'll make some arrangements to find someone for you to talk with.
在此之前 你若愿意参加小组倾诉
And until then, if you want to just sit in on a group.
也可以 交给我
It's OK. Uh... I got it.
艾登 你今天带了个朋友啊
Aidan, you brought a friend today.
对 各位 这是本
Yeah. Everyone, this is Ben.
你好 本
Hi, Ben.
你当过兵吗
You were a soldier?
对 在刚果民主共和国
Yes. In the Democratic Republic of Congo.
对 本是来 他只是来倾听的
Yeah, Ben's just... he's just here to listen.
好吧 如果本是来倾听的
Well, if Ben's going to listen,
那他得有倾听对象啊
he's going to need someone to listen to.
有人想说说吗
Does anyone have anything to say?
有 我有话要说
Yeah. I'll go.
我已经越来越好 进步很多
you know, I've been doing better. A lot better.
但是这周 由于某些原因
Uh... but this week, for some reason,
那种感觉又回来了
it's been coming back on me, and...
每当我睡觉时
when I sleep...
如果我睡着了
if I sleep - uh...
那些最糟糕的事就回来了
the worst things come back.
想跟我们谈谈那些最糟糕的事吗 艾登
Do you want to tell us about the worst things, Aidan?
可是 没什么新鲜的
Well, I mean, it's nothing new.
你们以前都听过
You guys have heard it all before.
他没听过
He hasn't.
# 从未见过你 #
Never saw you
# 从未听过你消息 #
Never heard you
# 可我知道你就在那里 #
But I knew that you were there